<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us356-0041.html" citation="356 U.S. 41" title="Ferguson v. St. Louis-San Francisco Ry. Co.">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p41">41</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>Ferguson v. St. Louis-San Francisco Ry. Co., <a href="./us356-0041.xml#p41">356 U.S. 41</a> (1958)</h1>
    <h2>Ferguson v. St. Louis-San Francisco Railway Co.</h2>
    <h2>No. 799</h2>
    <h4>Decided March 17, 1958</h4>
    <h2>ON PETITION FOR WRIT OF CERTIORARI</h2>
    <h2>TO THE SUPREME COURT OF MISSOURI</h2>
    <h2>Syllabus</h2>
    <p>In this case arising under the Federal Employers' Liability Act, held: the proofs were sufficient to submit to the jury the question whether employer negligence played a part in producing petitioner's injury. Therefore, certiorari is granted, the judgment below is reversed, and the case is remanded for further proceedings.</p>
    <p>Reported below: 307 S.W.2d 385.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The petition for writ of certiorari is granted. We hold that the proofs were sufficient to submit to the jury the question whether employer negligence played a part in producing the petitioner's injury. Wilkerson v. McCarthy, <a href="../us336/us336-0053.xml#p53">336 U. S. 53</a>; Rogers v. Missouri Pacific R. Co., <a href="../us352/us352-0500.xml#p500">352 U. S. 500</a>; Webb v. Illinois Central R. Co., <a href="../us352/us352-0512.xml#p512">352 U. S. 512</a>; Shaw v. Atlantic Coast Line R. Co., 353 U.S. 920; Futrelle v. Atlantic Coast Line R. Co., 353 U.S. 920; Deen v. Gulf, C. &amp; S.F. R. Co., 353 U.S. 925; Thomson v. Texas &amp; Pacific R. Co., 353 U.S. 926; Arnold v. Panhandle &amp; S.F. R. Co., <a href="../us353/us353-0360.xml#p360">353 U. S. 360</a>; Ringhiser v. Chesapeake &amp; O. R. Co., <a href="../us354/us354-0901.xml#p901">354 U. S. 901</a>; McBride v. Toledo Terminal R. Co., <a href="../us354/us354-0517.xml#p517">354 U. S. 517</a>; Gibson v. Thompson, <a href="../us355/us355-0018.xml#p18">355 U. S. 18</a>; Honeycutt v. Wabash R. Co., <a href="../us355/us355-0424.xml#p424">355 U. S. 424</a>. The judgment of the Supreme Court of Missouri is</p>
    <n id="p42">42</n>
    <p>reversed, and the case is remanded for further proceedings in conformity with this opinion.</p>
    <p>MR. JUSTICE HARLAN concurs in the result for the reasons given in his Memorandum in Gibson v. Thompson, <a href="../us355/us355-0018.xml#p18">355 U. S. 18</a>. For the reasons set forth in his opinion in Rogers v. Missouri Pacific R. Co., <a href="../us352/us352-0500.xml#p500">352 U. S. 500</a>, <a href="../us352/us352-0521.xml#p524">352 U. S. 524</a>.</p>
    <p>MR. JUSTICE FRANKFURTER is of the view that the writ of certiorari is improvidently granted.</p>
    <p>MR. JUSTICE WHITTAKER dissents.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
