<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us421-0993.html" citation="421 U.S. 993" title="RIDENS v. ILLINOIS">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p993">993</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>RIDENS v. ILLINOIS, (1975)</h4>
    <h2></h2>
    <h2>Frank C. RIDENS et al. v. State of ILLINOIS et al. No. 74-1003.</h2>
    <h2>Supreme Court of the United States</h2>
    <h4>May 27, 1975</h4>
    <p>On petition for writ of certiorari to the Supreme Court of Illinois.</p>
    <p>The petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.</p>
    <p>Mr. Justice BRENNAN, with whom Mr. Justice STEWART and Mr. Justice MARSHALL join, dissenting.</p>
    <p>Petitioners were convicted of selling allegedly obscene publications in violation of the Illinois Obscenity Statute, Ill.Rev.Stat.1969, c. 38, 11-20, and the obscenity ordinance of the city of Moline, Illinois. The Illinois Supreme Court affirmed their convictions. <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/illinois/supreme-court/1972/43974-5-0.html">51 Ill. 2d 410</a>, <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/illinois/supreme-court/1972/43974-5-0.html">282 N.E.2d 691</a> (1972). We granted the petition for certiorari and remanded the case for further consideration in light of Miller v. California, <a href="../us413/us413-0015.xml#p15">413 U.S. 15</a> (1973).</p>
    <n id="p994">994</n>
    <p>413 U.S. 912 (1973). On remand, the Illinois Supreme Court again affirmed the convictions.</p>
    <p>For the reasons stated in my dissent from the remand of this case, 413 U.S. 912, and because the present judgment was rendered after Miller, I would grant the petition and reverse.*</p>
    <p>Mr. Justice DOUGLAS, being of the view that any state or federal ban on, or regulation of, obscenity is prohibited by the Constitution, Roth v. United States, <a href="../us354/us354-0476.xml#p476">354 U.S. 476</a>, 508-514 (1957); Miller v. California, <a href="../us413/us413-0015.xml#p15">413 U.S. 15</a>, 42-47 ( 1973); Paris Adult Theatre I v. Slaton, <a href="../us413/us413-0049.xml#p49">413 U.S. 49</a>, 70-73 (1973), would grant certiorari and summarily reverse.</p>
    <h2>Footnotes</h2>
    <f n="*1"><a id="fn*1" href="#nf*1">Footnote *</a>
      <p>Although four of us would grant and reverse, the Justices who join this opinion do not insist that the case be decided on the merits.</p>
    </f>
  </opinion>
</case>
