<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us004-0353.html" citation="4 U.S. 353" title="HOLLINGSWORTH v. DUANE">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p353">353</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>HOLLINGSWORTH v. DUANE, <a href="./us004-0353.xml#p353">4 U.S. 353</a> (1801)</h1>
    <h2>Hollingsworth v. Duane.</h2>
    <h2>Circuit Court, Pennsylvania District.</h2>
    <h4>May Term, 1801</h4>
    <p>IN this case (which was an action for a libel) the defendant filed a plea to the jurisdiction of the Court, on the ground, that he, as well as the plaintiff, was a citizen of Pennsylvania. Issue being joined on that fact, it was found, by the Jury, that the defendant was not a citizen; and thereupon, in consequence of a previous agreement, a venire issued to ascertain the quantum of damages, which the verdict settled at 600 dollars. After</p>
    <n id="p354">354</n>
    <p>the verdict was given, it appeared that one of the jurors was an alien; and Dallas obtained a rule to show cause, why the verdict should not be set aside for that reason.</p>
    <p>On the argument, in support of the rule, it was contended, 1st. That the trial by jury, entire, was anxiously adopted by the United States, as well as by this state; including the right, and causes, of challenge as at common law, in civil and in criminal cases. 1 vol. State Laws, App. 55. s. 9. 11. (Dall. edit.) Ibid. 58. s. 25. 3 vol. 36. s. 9. 6. 4 vol. Acts Cong. p. 25. art. 8, 9. 1 vol. State Laws, p. 134. s. 4. Dall. edit. 2 vol. 802. s. 2. 3 vol. 606. s. 16. 2 vol. 264. s. 9. 12. 3. 1 vol. Acts Cong. 113. s. 30. Ibid. 68. s. 29. 2d. That on principle, as well as on authority, alienage was a cause of challenge to a juror before verdict. 3 State Laws, Const. art. 8. 1 vol. Acts Cong. Const. art. 6. Ibid. 67. s. 29. 1 Roll. Abr. 657. Co. Litt. 156. b. 3 Bl. Com. 362. Gilb. P. C. 94. 1 Dall. Rep. 74. 3d. That if the cause of challenge was unknown when the jury was qualified, it may be used to set aside the verdict, as for a mistrial. 3 Dall. Rep. 515. 11 Mod. 119. 2 Wood. 352. An. Reg. 1790. p. 46. 2 Ld. Raym. 1410. 1 Stra. 640. 1 vol. Acts Cong. 6. s. 17. 2 Stra. 1000. 593.</p>
    <p>E. Tilghman and Ingersoll, in opposition to the rule, contended, 1st. That, in Pennsylvania, alienage was not a cause of challenge to a juror. But, 2d. That the objection was too late after the juror was sworn, and the verdict was given.</p>
    <p>THE COURT.</p>
    <p>The COURT, after a long advisement upon the subject, seemed to think, that alienage might have been a cause of challenge, before the juror was sworn; but, upon an extensive review of the authorities, they decided, that advantage could not be taken of it, after verdict.</p>
    <p>Rule discharged. [<a id="nf1" href="#fn1">Footnote 1</a>]</p>
    <h2>Footnotes</h2>
    <f n="1"><a id="fn1" href="#nf1">Footnote 1</a>
      <p>Since the discussion of this case, the marshal has been directe d not to return aliens upon the panel; and, in many instances, when sliens have been returned, the state, as well as the federal, Courts have discharged them, upon their own application.</p>
    </f>
  </opinion>
</case>
