<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us004-0250.html" citation="4 U.S. 250" title="COCHRAN v. CUMMINGS">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p250">250</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>COCHRAN v. CUMMINGS, <a href="./us004-0250.xml#p250">4 U.S. 250</a> (1802)</h1>
    <h2>Cochran et al. v. Cummings.</h2>
    <h2>Supreme Court of Pennsylvania.</h2>
    <h4>December Term, 1802</h4>
    <p>CASE, for goods sold and delivered. There was a special defence, that the defendant had sold, and conveyed to the plaintiffs, a quantity of land in the county of Northumberland, in satisfaction of their demand; and the deed of conveyance, dated in June 1799, was produced. But the plaintiffs insisted, 1st. That they took the conveyance only as a collateral security: and, 2dly. That they were imposed upon by the defendant, as to the quality of the land.</p>
    <p>On the first point, the evidence was contradictory; and the COURT left it, implicitly, to be decided by the jury.</p>
    <p>On the second point, it was proved, that the defendant had represented the land as very valuable; saying, that it was such as would sell, in two or three years, for a price, from two to six dollars an acre: but, in fact, the land was a part of a mountain, commonly called 'Jack's Second Mountain;' so rude, that it could not be cultivated; and so steep, that it was inaccessible, even to take off the wood, without incalculable expense and labour. In the charge of the COURT, on this point, it was said,</p>
    <p>By SHIPPEN, Chief Justice:</p>
    <p>Wherever there is a gross misrepresentation of facts, relating to the subject of a contract, the contract is fraudulent and void. If, therefore, the jury shall be of opinion, that such a misrepresentation was made, in the present instance; they should consider the conveyance as no payment, although the plaintiffs agreed, under the deception, to accept it in satisfection; and the verdict must be for damages to the whole amount of the demand.</p>
    <p>Verdict, accordingly, for the plaintiffs' whole demand.</p>
    <p>Ingersoll, and Heatly, for the plaintiffs.</p>
    <p>M. Levy, and Porter, for the defendant.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
