<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us004-0283.html" citation="4 U.S. 283" title="WATSON v. INSURANCE CO OF NORTH AMERICA">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p283">283</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>WATSON v. INSURANCE CO OF NORTH AMERICA, (1803)</h4>
    <h2>(Dall.)</h2>
    <h2>Watson et al. v. The Insurance Company of North-America.</h2>
    <h2>Supreme Court of Pennsylvania.</h2>
    <h4>September Term, 1803</h4>
    <p>THIS was an action on a policy of insurance, in which the declaration was for a total loss. On the trial, it appeared, that the assured had demanded payment of a total loss, which the defendants refused to pay; but there was no evidence of an actual abandonment, or offer to abandon, to the underwriters, before the suit was instituted; and the proof was of a loss in its nature total. The jury gave a verdict, in favor of the plaintiff, finding damages, as for a partial loss; subject to the opinion of the Court, upon a motion for a new trial, to consider two points reserved: 1st. Whether a previous abandonment, or offer to abandon, was indispensably necessary, to enable the plaintiff to recover in this suit? And, 2d. Whether, on a declaration for a total loss, and proof of a loss in its nature total, the jury can give damages for less than a total loss?</p>
    <p>After argument by M. Levy and Lewis, for the plaintiffs; and by Moylan, E. Tilghman, and Ingersoll, for the defendants, the COURT ( consisting of SHIPPEN,Chief Justice, and YEATES and SMITH, Justices) were of opinion, that the jury might find damages for a partial loss; although the declaration claimed for a total loss; and although there was no proof of an actual abandonment, or an offer to abandon, to the underwriters.</p>
    <p>But BRACKENRIDGE, Justice, said, that he thought there was sufficient evidence at the trial, to induce the jury to find an abandonment; and, on that ground alone, he concurred, in refusing a new trial.</p>
    <p>For, the general ground, on which the opinion of the rest of the Court was founded, did not appear to him so conclusive, and so satisfactory, as it did to them.</p>
    <p>Motion for a new trial refused: and judgment rendered on the verdict for the plaintiffs.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
