<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us064-0481.html" citation="64 U.S. 481" title="Clifton v. Sheldon">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p481">481</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>Clifton v. Sheldon, 64 U.S. 481 (1859)</h1>
    <h2>Clifton v. Sheldon</h2>
    <h2>64 U.S. (23 How.) 481</h2>
    <h2>APPEAL FROM THE CIRCUIT COURT OF THE UNITED</h2>
    <h2>STATES FOR THE SOUTHERN DISTRICT OF NEW YORK</h2>
    <h2>Syllabus</h2>
    <p>Where a decree was made by the circuit court, sitting in admiralty, that two persons should pay freight, one in the sum of $583.84, and the other in the sum of $1,754.22, and the latter only appealed to this Court, the appeal must be dismissed, as the amount in controversy is less than $2,000.</p>
    <p>The rights of the two were distinct and independent, but if the freight be considered a joint matter, both should have joined in the appeal.</p>
    <p>The facts are stated in the opinion of the Court.</p>
    <n id="p483">483</n>
    <p>MR. JUSTICE NELSON delivered the opinion of the Court.</p>
    <p>A motion has been made, on the part of the appellee, to dismiss the appeal, for the want of jurisdiction.</p>
    <p>A libel was filed by Clifton in the district court to recover freight on the two hundred and sixty-nine bales of cotton and nine bags of wool. Brower and Sheldon appeared as claimants and contested the claim for the freight. Brower claimed sixty-seven of the two hundred and sixty-nine bales, and Sheldon two hundred and two bales. The district court dismissed the libel.</p>
    <p>On appeal to the circuit court, this decree was reversed and decree rendered in favor of the libellant for the amount of the freight, $2,338.06; that J. W. Brower, claimant of a portion of the cotton, pay to the libellant the sum of $583.84, being the freight on the cotton claimed by him in the suit, and that the</p>
    <n id="p484">484</n>
    <p>claimant, W. H. Sheldon, pay for the portion claimed by him the sum of $1,754.22. Sheldon appealed from the decree to this Court.</p>
    <p>The motion is now made to dismiss the appeal on the ground that the decree against Sheldon is less than $2,000, and which is apparent from a perusal of the decree. The sum decreed against him is only $1,754.22.</p>
    <p>The freight was separately awarded against the claimants, in proportion to the cotton shipped by each one. The rights of each were distinct and independent.</p>
    <p>But if it were otherwise, and the whole of the freight jointly against the claimants, the appeal must still be dismissed, as then the claimants should have joined in it.</p>
    <p>Motion to dismiss granted.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
