<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us332-0826.html" citation="332 U.S. 826" title="CHASE NATIONAL BANK OF CITY OF NEW YORK V. CHESTON">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p826">826</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>CHASE NATIONAL BANK OF CITY OF NEW YORK V. CHESTON, <a href="./us332-0826.xml#p826">332 U.S. 826</a> (1947)</h1>
    <h2>The CHASE NATIONAL BANK OF THE CITY of NEW YORK, as Trustees, etc., et al., petitioners, v. J. Hamilton CHESTON et al. No. 178.</h2>
    <h2>Same v. METROPOLITAN LIFE INSURANCE COMPANY. No. 179.</h2>
    <h2>SAME v. CENTRAL HANOVER BANK AND TRUST COMPANY et al., as Trustees, etc. No. 180.</h2>
    <h2>SAME v. NATIONAL CITY BANK OF NEW YORK, as Trustee, etc. No. 181.</h2>
    <h2>SAME v. John C. TRAPHAGEN et al. No. 182.</h2>
    <h2>SAME v. James G. BLAINE et al. No. 183.</h2>
    <h2>The CHICAGO, ROCK ISLAND &amp; PACIFIC RAILWAY COMPANY, petitioner, v. Supreme Court of the United States</h2>
    <h4>November 17, 1947</h4>
    <p>METROPOLITAN LIFE INSURANCE COMPANY. No. 184.</p>
    <p>[ Chase National Bank of City of New York v. Cheston <a href="./us332-0826.xml#p826">332 U.S. 826</a> (1947) ][826-Continued.]</p>
    <p>SAME v. CENTRAL HANOVER BANK AND TRUST COMPANY et al., as Trustees, etc. No. 185.</p>
    <p>SAME v. The NATIONAL CITY BANK OF NEW YORK, as Trustee, etc. No. 186.</p>
    <p>SAME v. J. Hamilton CHESTON et al. No. 187.</p>
    <p>SAME v. John C. TRAPHAGEN et al. No. 188.</p>
    <p>SAME v. James G. BLAINE et al. No. 189.</p>
    <p>Messrs. John Gerdes, of New York City, and Henry F. Tenney, of Chicago, Ill., for debtor-petitioner, Chicago R. I. &amp; P. Ry. Co.</p>
    <p>Mr. Loy N. McIntosh, of Chicago, Ill. (Messrs. Gann, Secord, Stead &amp; McIntosh, of counsel), for the Protective Committee for Chicago Rock Island and P. Ry. Co.'s 7% and 6% Preferred Stock.</p>
    <p>Messrs. Alexander &amp; Green, of New York City, and Winston, Strawn &amp; Shaw, of Chicago, Ill. (Messrs. Frank H. Towner, of Chicago, Ill., and Edward W. Bourne, of New York City, of counsel), for Protective Committee for Chicago, Rock Island and Pacific Railway Company General Mortgage Bonds due January 1, 1988.</p>
    <p>Messrs. White &amp; Case, of New York City, and Winston, Strawn &amp; Shaw, of Chicago, Ill. (Messrs. Frank H. Towner, of Chicago, Ill., and Jesse E. Waid, of New York City, of counsel), for Bankers Trust Co. and others. [826-Continued.]</p>
    <p>Messrs. Root, Ballantine, Harlan, Bushby &amp; Palmer, of New York City ( Messrs. Wilkie Bushby and Joseph Schreiber, both of New York City, of counsel), for Metropolitan Life Ins. Co.</p>
    <p>Messrs. Rathbone, Perry, Kelley &amp; Drye, of New York City (Mr. Alexander M. Lewis, of New York City, of counsel), for Central Hanover Bank and Trust Co. et al.</p>
    <p>Messrs. Shearman &amp; Sterling &amp; Wright, of New York City (Mr. Sanford H. E. Freund, of New York City, of counsel), for National City Bank of New York et al.</p>
    <p>Messrs. Beekman &amp; Bogue, of New York City (Mr. Edward K. Hanlon, of New York City, of counsel), for Protective Committee for the Holders of First Mortgage 4 1/2% Bonds of The Rock Island, Arkansas and Louisiana Railroad Company.</p>
    <p>Messrs. Cahill, Gordon, Zachry &amp; Reindel, of New York City (Mr. Daniel James, of New York City, of counsel), for Protective Committee for Choctaw, Oklahoma &amp; G. R. Co. et al.</p>
    <p>Nov. 17, 1947.</p>
    <p>The petition for rehearing is denied.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
