<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us471-0083.html" citation="471 U.S. 83" title="BOARD OF TRUSTEES OF SCARSDALE v. McCREARY">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p83">83</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>BOARD OF TRUSTEES OF SCARSDALE v. McCREARY, <a href="./us471-0083.xml#p83">471 U.S. 83</a> (1985)</h1>
    <h4>BOARD OF TRUSTEES OF THE VILLAGE OF SCARSDALE ET AL. v. McCREARY ET AL. CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE SECOND CIRCUIT No. 84-277. Argued February 20, 1985 Decided March 27, 1985</h4>
    <p><a href="http://cases.justia.com/us-court-of-appeals/F2/739/716/">739 F.2d 716</a>, affirmed by an equally divided Court.</p>
    <p>Marvin E. Frankel argued the cause for petitioners. With him on the briefs was Marc D. Stern. Marvin Schwartz argued the cause for respondents and filed a brief for respondents Scarsdale Creche Committee et al. Vincent K. Gilmore filed a brief for respondents McCreary et al.*</p>
    <p>[Footnote *] Briefs of amici curiae urging reversal were filed for the American Civil Liberties Union et al. by Burt Neuborne, Charles S. Sims, Norman Dorsen, and Steven R. Shapiro; for the American Jewish Committee et al. by Samuel Rabinove; and for the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith et al. by Ruti G. Teitel, Meyer Eisenberg, Justin J. Finger, and Jeffrey P. Sinensky.</p>
    <p>Solicitor General Lee, Acting Assistant Attorney General Willard, and Deputy Solicitor General Bator filed a brief for the United States as amicus curiae urging affirmance.</p>
    <p>Steven Frederick McDowell filed a brief for the Catholic League for Religious and Civil Rights as amicus curiae.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The judgment is affirmed by an equally divided Court.</p>
    <p>JUSTICE POWELL took no part in the decision of this case.</p>
    <n id="p84">84</n>
  </opinion>
</case>
