<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us311-0054.html" citation="311 U.S. 54" title="Crane-Johnson Co. v. Helvering">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p54">54</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>Crane-Johnson Co. v. Helvering, (1940)</h4>
    <h2>Crane-Johnson Company v. Helvering</h2>
    <h2>No. 8</h2>
    <h4>Argued October 23, 1940</h4>
    <h4>Decided November 12, 1940</h4>
    <h2></h2>
    <h2>CERTIORARI TO THE CIRCUIT COURT OF APPEALS</h2>
    <h2>FOR THE EIGHTH CIRCUIT</h2>
    <h2>Syllabus</h2>
    <p>Decided on the authority of Helvering v. Northwest Steel Rolling Mills, ante p. <a href="./us311-0046.xml#p46">311 U. S. 46</a>.</p>
    <p>105 F.2d 740 affirmed.</p>
    <p>Certiorari, 309 U.S. 692, to review the affirmance of a decision of the Board of Tax Appeals, 38 B.T.A. 1355, which sustained the Commissioner's determination of a tax deficiency.</p>
    <p>MR. JUSTICE BLACK delivered the opinion of the Court.</p>
    <p>Because of a previously existing deficit, petitioner corporation was prohibited by state law [<a id="nf1" href="#fn1">Footnote 1</a>] from distributing as dividends its profits earned in 1936. Notwithstanding this state prohibition, the Commissioner held respondent liable under the 1936 Revenue Act [<a id="nf2" href="#fn2">Footnote 2</a>] for surtax on undistributed profits. The Board of Tax Appeals sustained</p>
    <n id="p55">55</n>
    <p>the Commissioner, [<a id="nf3" href="#fn3">Footnote 3</a>] and the Circuit Court of Appeals affirmed. [<a id="nf4" href="#fn4">Footnote 4</a>] On a similar state of facts, the Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit held undistributed profits exempt from surtax. [<a id="nf5" href="#fn5">Footnote 5</a>] We granted certiorari in both cases to resolve this conflict. [<a id="nf6" href="#fn6">Footnote 6</a>] The legal questions here presented are in all respects the same as those presented in Helvering v. Northwest Steel Rolling Mills, ante, p. <a href="./us311-0046.xml#p46">311 U. S. 46</a>, and, on the authority of that case, the decision below is</p>
    <p>Affirmed.</p>
    <f n="1"><a id="fn1" href="#nf1">Footnote 1</a>
      <p>"The directors of corporations must not make dividends except from the surplus profits arising from the business thereof. . . ." N.D.Comp.Laws (Supp. 1925) section 4543.</p>
    </f>
    <f n="2"><a id="fn2" href="#nf2">Footnote 2</a>
      <p>49 Stat. 1648, 1655.</p>
    </f>
    <f n="3"><a id="fn3" href="#nf3">Footnote 3</a>
      <p>38 B.T.A. 1355.</p>
    </f>
    <f n="4"><a id="fn4" href="#nf4">Footnote 4</a>
      <p>105 F.2d 740.</p>
    </f>
    <f n="5"><a id="fn5" href="#nf5">Footnote 5</a>
      <p>Northwest Steel Rolling Mills v. Commissioner, 110 F.2d 286.</p>
    </f>
    <f n="6"><a id="fn6" href="#nf6">Footnote 6</a>
      <p>309 U.S. 692; 311 U.S. 629.</p>
    </f>
  </opinion>
</case>
