<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<case source="us282-0827.html" citation="282 U.S. 827" title="MCCAUGHN v. HERSHEY CHOCOLATE CO.">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p827">827</n>
    <h>U.S. Supreme Court</h>
    <h>MCCAUGHN v. HERSHEY CHOCOLATE CO., <a href="./us282-0827.xml#p827">282 U.S. 827</a> (1930)</h>
    <h> <a href="./us282-0827.xml#p827">282 U.S. 827</a></h>
    <h>B. D. McCAUGHN, Collector, petitioner, v. HERSHEY CHOCOLATE CO. No. 426. </h>
    <h>ESTATE OF E. LEDERER, Collector, petitioner, v. HERSHEY CHOCOLATE CO. No. 427.</h>
    <h>ESTATE OF B. F. DAVIS, Collector, petitioner, v. HERSHEY CHOCOLATE CO. No. 428.</h>
    <h>ESTATE OF E. LEDERER, Collector, petitioner v. HERSHEY CHOCOLATE CO. No. 429.</h>
    <h>B. D. McCAUGHN, Collector, petitioner, v. HERSHEY CHOCOLATE CO. No. 430.</h>
    <h>ESTATE OF B. F. DAVIS, Collector, petitioner, v. HERSHEY CHOCOLATE CO. No. 431.</h>
    <h>ESTATE of B. F. DAVIS, Collector, petitioner, v. KLEIN CHOCOLATE CO. No. 432.</h>
    <h>ESTATE OF E. LEDERER, Collector petitioner, v. KLEIN CHOCOLATE CO. No. 433.</h>
    <h>ESTATE OF E. LEDERER, Collector, petitioner, v. KLEIN CHOCOLATE CO. No. 434. [827-Continued.]</h>
    <h>B. D. McCAUGHN, Collector, petitioner, v. KLEIN CHOCOLATE CO. No. 435.</h>
    <h>ESTATE OF E. LEDERER, Collector, petitioner, v. WILBUR-SUCHARD CHOCOLATE CO. No. 436.</h>
    <h>ESTATE OF E. LEDERER, Collector, petitioner, v. WILBUR-SUCHARD CHOCOLATE CO. No. 437.</h>
    <h>B. D. McCAUGHN, Collector, petitioner, v. WILBUR-SUCHARD CHOCOLATE CO. No. 438.</h>
    <h>ESTATE OF B. F. DAVIS, Collector, petitioner, v. YORK CHOCOLATE CO. No. 439.</h>
    <h>ESTATE OF E. LEDERER, Collector, petitioner, v. YORK CHOCOLATE CO. No. 440.</h>
    <h>B. D. McCAUGHN, Collector, petitioner, v. YORK CHOCOLATE CO. No. 441. Supreme Court of the United States</h>
    <h>October 20, 1930</h>
    <p>and</p>
    <p>The Attorney General and Claude R. Branch, of Providence, R. I., Sp. Asst. to Atty. Gen., for the Collectors.</p>
    <p>Oct. 20, 1930.</p>
    <p>Petition for writs of certiorari to the United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit granted.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
