<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us012-0358.html" citation="12 U.S. 358" title="THE FRANCES">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p358">358</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>THE FRANCES, <a href="./us012-0358.xml#p358">12 U.S. 358</a> (1814)</h1>
    <h2>THE FRANCES, BOYER, MASTER. (Kennedy's claim.)</h2>
    <h4>Mar. 12, 1814</h4>
    <p>THIS was likewise a case of goods by the Frances, condemned in the Circuit Court of Rhode Island. They were claimed by Duncan Kennedy, an American citizen, who appealed to this Court.</p>
    <p>The case was submitted to the Court without argument.</p>
    <p>Saturday, March 12th. Absent. LIVINGSTON, J.</p>
    <p>MARSHALL, Ch. J. delivered the opinion of the Court as follows:</p>
    <p>Duncan Kennedy, surviving partner of the house of George Stayley &amp; Co. merchants of New York, claims eight boxes of merchandize, part of the cargo of the ship Frances, as his property.</p>
    <n id="p359">359</n>
    <p>The invoice is headed</p>
    <p>'Glasgow, 8th July, 1812.</p>
    <p>'Messrs. George Stayley &amp; Co.</p>
    <p>'Receive from James Smith.'</p>
    <p>A letter from James Smith to George Stayley &amp; Co. in speaking of the goods, terms them 'our goods,' and does not, in any manner, indicate that they are the goods of Stayley &amp; Co. He concludes his letter with saying, 'As it is to be hoped the trade will now open, 'I shall expect your instructions saying what goods 'are best suited for the market.'</p>
    <p>The bill of lading is filled up with the name of George Stayley &amp; Co. ' on account and risk as per invoice.'</p>
    <p>There are several letters from George Stayley, in Glasgow, to his father; but none of them indicate an opinion that the property of the goods was in George Stayley &amp; Co:</p>
    <p>The sentence, condemning these goods, must be affirmed.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
