<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us396-0009.html" citation="396 U.S. 9" title="BERNARD v. NEW YORK CITY EMPLOYEES' RETIREMENT SYSTEM">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p9">9</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>BERNARD v. NEW YORK CITY EMPLOYEES' RETIREMENT SYSTEM, (1969)</h4>
    <h2></h2>
    <h4>BERNARD v. NEW YORK CITY EMPLOYEES' RETIREMENT SYSTEM ET AL. APPEAL FROM THE APPELLATE DIVISION OF THE SUPREME COURT OF NEW YORK, FIRST JUDICIAL DEPARTMENT No. 177, Misc. Decided October 13, 1969</h4>
    <p>Appeal dismissed.</p>
    <p>J. Lee Rankin and Stanley Buchsbaum for New York City Employees' Retirement System, and George N. Kanoff for Lipori, appellees.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The motions to dismiss are granted and the appeal is dismissed for want of a substantial federal question.</p>
    <p>(1969) (1969) "&gt;</p>
    <p>U.S. Supreme Court</p>
    <h4>SELLERS v. UNITED STATES, (1969)</h4>
    <p>SELLERS v. UNITED STATES ON PETITION FOR WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE FIFTH CIRCUIT No. 264, Misc. Decided October 13, 1969</p>
    <p>Certiorari granted; <a href="http://cases.justia.com/us-court-of-appeals/F2/406/465/">406 F.2d 465</a>, vacated and remanded to District Court.</p>
    <p>Howard Moore, Jr., for petitioner.</p>
    <p>Solicitor General Griswold for the United States.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>Upon consideration of the suggestion of the Solicitor General and an examination of the entire record, the motion for leave to proceed in forma pauperis and the petition for a writ of certiorari are granted. The judgment is vacated and the case is remanded to the United States District Court for the Northern District of Georgia for further consideration in light of Alderman v. United States, <a href="../us394/us394-0165.xml#p165">394 U.S. 165</a>.</p>
    <n id="p10">10</n>
  </opinion>
</case>
