<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us239-0655.html" citation="239 U.S. 655" title="ST. LOUIS &amp; SAN FRANCISCO RAILROAD CO. v. PUBLIC">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p655">655</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>ST. LOUIS &amp; SAN FRANCISCO RAILROAD CO. v. PUBLIC, (1915)</h4>
    <h2></h2>
    <h2>ST. LOUIS &amp; SAN FRANCISCO RAILROAD COMPANY Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 92.</h2>
    <h2>ATCHISON, TOPEKA, &amp; SANTA FE RAILWAY COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 93.</h2>
    <h2>ST. LOUIS SOUTHWESTERN RAILWAY COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 94.</h2>
    <h2>CHICAGO, ROCK ISLAND, &amp; PACIFIC RAILWAY COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 95.</h2>
    <h2>ST. LOUIS, KANSAS CITY, &amp; COLORADO RAILROAD COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 96.</h2>
    <h2>KANSAS CITY SOUTHERN RAILWAY COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 97.</h2>
    <h2>MISSOURI PACIFIC PAILWAY COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 98.</h2>
    <h2>ST. LOUIS, IRON MOUNTAIN, &amp; SOUTHERN RAILWAY COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 99.</h2>
    <h2>MISSOURI, KANSAS, &amp; TEXAS RAILWAY COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 100. [655-Continued.]</h2>
    <h2>CHICAGO, BURLINGTON, &amp; QUINCY RAILROAD COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 101.</h2>
    <h2>CHICAGO, MILWAUKEE, &amp; ST. PAUL RAILWAY COMPANY, Appellant, v. PURBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 102.</h2>
    <h2>CHICAGO &amp; ALTON RAILROAD COMPANY, Appellant, v. PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MISSOURI et al. No. 103.</h2>
    <h2>Supreme Court of the United States</h2>
    <h4>November 29, 1915</h4>
    <p>Messrs. Frank Hagerman and Edward J. White for appellants.</p>
    <p>Messrs. John T. Barker and William G. Busby for appellees.</p>
    <p>Dismissed with costs, on motion of counsel for the appellant.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
