<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us379-0693.html" citation="379 U.S. 693" title="Forty-fourth General Assembly v. Lucas">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p693">693</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>Forty-fourth General Assembly v. Lucas, <a href="./us379-0693.xml#p693">379 U.S. 693</a> (1965)</h1>
    <h2>Forty-fourth General Assembly of Colorado v. Lucas</h2>
    <h2>No. 661</h2>
    <h4>Decided February 1, 1965</h4>
    <h2>APPEAL FROM THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</h2>
    <h2>FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLORADO</h2>
    <h2>Judgment with respect to federal questions affirmed; judgment with respect to other questions vacated, and cause remanded.</h2>
    <h2>Reported below: <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp/232/797/1748722/">232 F. Supp. 797</a>.</h2>
    <h2>PER CURIAM.</h2>
    <h4>Insofar as the judgment of the District Court decides federal questions, it is affirmed. Insofar as the judgment decides other questions, it is vacated, and the cause is remanded for further consideration in light of the supervening decision of the Colorado Supreme Court in White v. Anderson, ___ Colo. ___, <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/colorado/supreme-court/1964/21252.html">394 P.2d 333</a> (1964).</h4>
    <h2>MR. JUSTICE CLARK, MR. JUSTICE HARLAN, MR. JUSTICE STEWART, and MR. JUSTICE GOLDBERG, concurring.</h2>
    <h2>It is our understanding that the Court's disposition of this case leaves it open to the District Court to abstain on the question as to the severability of the various provisions of Amendment No. 7, pending resolution of that issue with reasonable promptitude in further state court proceedings. We deem it appropriate explicitly to state our view that this is the course which the District Court should follow. On this basis, we join the Court's opinion.</h2>
  </opinion>
</case>
