<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us379-0131.html" citation="379 U.S. 131" title="COLORADO INTERSTATE GAS v. STATE CORP. COMM. OF KANSAS">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p131">131</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>COLORADO INTERSTATE GAS v. STATE CORP. COMM. OF KANSAS, <a href="./us379-0131.xml#p131">379 U.S. 131</a> (1964)</h1>
    <h4>COLORADO INTERSTATE GAS CO. v. STATE CORPORATION COMMISSION OF KANSAS ET AL. APPEAL FROM THE SUPREME COURT OF KANSAS. No. 75. Decided November 23, 1964.*</h4>
    <p>[Footnote *] Together with No. 83, Northern Natural Gas Co. et al. v. State Corporation Commission of Kansas et al., and No. 140, Kansas-Nebraska Natural Gas Co., Inc. v. State Corporation Commission of Kansas et al., also on appeal from the same court.</p>
    <p>Appeals dismissed and certiorari denied.</p>
    <p>Reported below: 192 Kan. 1, <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/kansas/supreme-court/1963/41-515-0.html">386 P.2d 266</a>; 192 Kan. 29, <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/kansas/supreme-court/1963/42-175-0.html">386 P.2d 288</a>.</p>
    <p>Lewis M. Poe, Jr., James Lawrence White and Malcolm Miller for appellant in No. 75.</p>
    <p>F. Vinson Roach, Patrick J. McCarthy, Mark H. Adams, Mark H. Adams II, Joe Rolston, Conrad C. Mount and Charles V. Wheeler for appellants in No. 83.</p>
    <p>James D. Conway, Mark H. Adams, Mark H. Adams II, Joe Rolston and Douglas Gleason for appellant in No. 140.</p>
    <p>Richard C. Byrd and Dale M. Stucky for State Corporation Commission of Kansas et al., and Wendell J. Doggett, Jeff A. Robertson, G. R. Redding and Thomas M. Lofton for Panhandle Eastern Pipe Line Co., appellees.</p>
    <p>Solicitor General Cox, Richard A. Solomon, Howard E. Wahrenbrock and Peter H. Schiff for the Federal Power Commission, as amicus curiae, in opposition.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The motions to dismiss are granted and the appeals are dismissed for want of jurisdiction. Treating the papers whereon the appeals were taken as petitions for writs of certiorari, certiorari is denied.</p>
    <p>MR. JUSTICE WHITE took no part in the consideration or decision of these cases.</p>
    <n id="p132">132</n>
  </opinion>
</case>
