<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<case source="us406-0813.html" citation="406 U.S. 813" title="Aikens v. California">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p813">813</n>
    <h>U.S. Supreme Court</h>
    <h>Aikens v. California, <a href="./us406-0813.xml#p813">406 U.S. 813</a> (1972)</h>
    <h>Aikens v. California</h>
    <h>No. 68-5027</h>
    <h>Argued January 17, 1972</h>
    <h>Decided June 7, 1972</h>
    <h><a href="./us406-0813.xml#p813">406 U.S. 813</a></h>
    <h>CERTIORARI TO THE SUPREME COURT OF CALIFORNIA</h>
    <h>Syllabus</h>
    <p>California Supreme Court decision invalidating death penalty under state constitution has mooted this case, where certiorari was granted to consider whether death penalty comports with Federal Constitution.</p>
    <p><a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/california/supreme-court/2d/70/369.html">70 Cal. 2d 369</a>, 450 P.2d 258, certiorari dismissed.</p>
    <n id="p814">814</n>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>Petitioner in this case, which has been orally argued and is now sub judice, has filed a Suggestion of Mootness and Motion for Remand based on the intervening decision of the California Supreme Court in People v. Anderson, <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/california/supreme-court/3d/6/628.html">6 Cal. 3d 628</a>, 493 P.2d 880 (1972). That decision declared capital punishment in California unconstitutional under Art. 1, § 6, of the state constitution. The decision rested on an adequate state ground, and the State's petition for writ of certiorari was denied. <a href="./us406-0091.xml#p98">406 U. S. 98</a>. The California Supreme Court declared in the Anderson case that its decision was fully retroactive, and stated that any prisoner currently under sentence of death could petition a superior court to modify its judgment. Petitioner thus no longer faces a realistic threat of execution, and the issue on which certiorari was granted -- the constitutionality of the death penalty under the Federal Constitution -- is now moot in his case. Accordingly, the writ of certiorari is dismissed.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
