<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us002-0125.html" citation="2 U.S. 125" title="LEECH v. ARMITAGE">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p125">125</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>LEECH v. ARMITAGE, <a href="./us002-0125.xml#p125">2 U.S. 125</a> (1791)</h1>
    <h2>Leech v. Armitage*</h2>
    <h2>Supreme Court of Pennsylvania</h2>
    <h4>April Term, 1791</h4>
    <p>This was an action of trespass for cutting trees. The defendant pleaded Liberum Tenementum; and the plaintiff replied Liberum Tenementum suum absque hoc, &amp;'c. The trial came on at Nisi Prius, in Montgomery County, before The Chief Justice, and Judge Shippen, on the 28th April, 1791.</p>
    <p>A preliminary question arising, who should open the cause, it was decided By The Court, after argument, that the proof of the issue lay upon the defendant: and that he, therefore, ought to begin. The Chief Justice added, that in all cases, the party who is first in the affirmative ought regularly to open; and referred to Forsythe versus Jones, tried at Nisi Prius, in Chester County, where the same point was ruled.</p>
    <p>On the trial of the cause, the defendant gave in evidence the record of a trial, verdict, and judgment, between the same parties, at a former period; to wit, in the year 1755. The plaintiff thereupon offered to prove by a witness, who was present at the former trial, that the evidence, now given by the plaintiff, was not then produced, nor discovered: But the proof was objected to, and the Court refused to admit it.</p>
    <p>By the Court: It would be too dangerous to trust to the recollection of a witness in so old a transaction, in order to shake the strength of the evidence, which the record imports.</p>
    <h2>Footnotes</h2>
    <p>[Footnote *] Decided at Montgomery, Nifi Prius.[ Leech v. Armitage</p>
    <f n="2"><a id="fn2" href="#nf2">Footnote 2</a>
      <p>U.S. 125 (1791) ]</p>
    </f>
  </opinion>
</case>
