<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us372-0770.html" citation="372 U.S. 770" title="PATTERSON v. NEWPORT NEWS REDEVELOP. &amp;amp; HOUSING AUTH.">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p770">770</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>PATTERSON v. NEWPORT NEWS REDEVELOP. &amp; HOUSING AUTH., <a href="./us372-0770.xml#p770">372 U.S. 770</a> (1963)</h1>
    <h4>PATTERSON ET AL. v. NEWPORT NEWS REDEVELOPMENT &amp; HOUSING AUTHORITY. APPEAL FROM THE SUPREME COURT OF APPEALS OF VIRGINIA. No. 896, Misc. Decided April 22, 1963.</h4>
    <p>Appeal dismissed and certiorari denied.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The appeal is dismissed. Treating the papers whereon the appeal was taken as a petition for writ of certiorari, certiorari is denied.</p>
    <n id="p771">771</n>
    <p><a href="./us372-0770.xml#p770">372 U.S. 770</a> (1963) <a href="./us372-0770.xml#p770">372 U.S. 770</a> (1963) "&gt;</p>
    <p>U.S. Supreme Court</p>
    <h4>HAYNES v. FLORIDA, <a href="./us372-0770.xml#p770">372 U.S. 770</a> (1963)</h4>
    <p><a href="./us372-0770.xml#p770">372 U.S. 770</a> HAYNES v. FLORIDA. ON MOTION FOR LEAVE TO FILE PETITION FOR WRIT OF HABEAS CORPUS. No. 37, Misc. Decided April 22, 1963.</p>
    <p>Motion for leave to file petition for writ of habeas corpus denied; certiorari granted; judgment vacated; and case remanded.</p>
    <p>Petitioner pro se.</p>
    <p>Richard W. Ervin, Attorney General of Florida, and A. G. Spicola, Jr., Special Assistant Attorney General, for respondent.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The motion for leave to proceed in forma pauperis is granted. The motion for leave to file a petition for writ of habeas corpus is denied. Treating the papers submitted as a petition for writ of certiorari to the Supreme Court of Florida, certiorari is granted. On writ of certiorari, the judgment is vacated and the case is remanded for further consideration in light of Gideon v. Wainwright, <a href="./us372-0335.xml#p335">372 U.S. 335</a>.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
