<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us116-0401.html" citation="116 U.S. 401" title="Ex Parte Brown">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p401">401</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>Ex Parte Brown, <a href="./us116-0401.xml#p401">116 U.S. 401</a> (1886)</h1>
    <h2>Ex Parte Brown</h2>
    <h4>Submitted January 13, 1886</h4>
    <h4>Decided January 18, 1886</h4>
    <h2>ORIGINAL</h2>
    <h2>Syllabus</h2>
    <p>The dismissal of a cause by the supreme court of a territory, because errors had not been assigned according to the roles of practice applicable to the form of action, is a judgment which can only be reviewed by writ of error or appeal, as the case may be.</p>
    <p>This was a motion for leave to file a petition for a writ of mandamus. The petition, which accompanied the motion, showed that the petitioners commenced a suit in ejectment in the Territory of Washington on the 10th of July, 1854; that the defendant answered, denying the plaintiff's right to recover and setting up various separate defenses; that the plaintiffs demurred; that the court overruled the demurrer; that the plaintiffs having elected to stand upon the ruling of the court on the demurrer, the case was dismissed; that the plaintiffs thereupon appealed to the supreme court of the territory; that transcripts of the record were duly filed in the supreme court and the causes removed and docketed there; that a motion was made by defendant to dismiss the appeal because the action was at law and could be reexamined only on writ of error; that the motion was sustained and judgment entered accordingly, and that the amount in controversy was largely in excess of $5,000. The prayer of the petition was for a writ of mandamus to the supreme court of the territory directing it to set aside the judgment, to reinstate the case, and to decide it on the merits.</p>
    <n id="p402">402</n>
    <p>MR. CHIEF JUSTICE WAITE delivered the opinion of the Court.</p>
    <p>This motion is denied. According to the petition, the court entertained jurisdiction of the cause, but dismissed it for want of due prosecution -- that is to say because errors had not been assigned in accordance with the rules of practice applicable to the form of the action. This is a judgment which can only be reviewed by writ of error or appeal, as the case may be. Mandamus lies to compel a court to take jurisdiction in a proper case, but not to control its discretion while acting within its jurisdiction. This rule is elementary. Ex Parte Morgan, <a href="../us114/us114-0174.xml#p174">114 U. S. 174</a>, and cases cited.</p>
    <p>Motion denied.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
