<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us245-0048.html" citation="245 U.S. 48" title="Jones v. ICC">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p48">48</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>Jones v. ICC, (1917)</h4>
    <h2>Jones v. Interstate Commerce Commission</h2>
    <h2>No. 340</h2>
    <h4>Argued October 3, 1917</h4>
    <h4>Decided November 5, 1917</h4>
    <h2></h2>
    <h2>APPEAL FROM THE SUPREME COURT</h2>
    <h2>OF THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA</h2>
    <h2>Syllabus</h2>
    <p>Decided on the authority of Smith v. Interstate Commerce Commission, ante, <a href="./us245-0033.xml#p33">245 U. S. 33</a>.</p>
    <p>Affirmed.</p>
    <p>The case is stated in the opinion.</p>
    <p>MR. JUSTICE McKENNA delivered the opinion of the court.</p>
    <p>This case was submitted with Smith v. Interstate Commerce Commission, ante, <a href="./us245-0033.xml#p33">245 U. S. 33</a> and <a href="./us245-0047.xml#p47">245 U. S. 47</a>. Like them, it is a proceeding to compel appellant to</p>
    <n id="p49">49</n>
    <p>answer certain questions asked him by the Interstate Commerce Commission. It was based on a petition like the petitions in those cases, to which there was a like reply.</p>
    <p>The court entered an order requiring appellant to answer the following questions asked by counsel for the Commission:</p>
    <p>"I will ask you if you distributed in the State of Alabama on behalf of the Louisville &amp; Nashville Railroad campaign funds favoring the election of a certain candidate?"</p>
    <p>"I show you Ledger H, folio 454, from the records of the Louisville &amp; Nashville Railroad, showing certain vouchers sent you in Alabama for various amounts, and will ask you how you expended the money represented by these vouchers, taking the first voucher as a beginning."</p>
    <p>"I will ask you whether or not you have personal knowledge of funds of the Louisville &amp; Nashville Railroad and of the Nashville, Chattanooga &amp; St. Louis Railway used to the extent of thousands of dollars for political campaign purposes in the State of Alabama. "</p>
    <n id="p50">50</n>
    <p>"I will ask you do you know of any campaign funds being expended by the Louisville &amp; Nashville Railroad and the Nashville, Chattanooga &amp; St. Louis Railway in the State of Alabama through any attorney under a subterfuge of paying the attorney a bill for professional services?"</p>
    <p>"Do you know of any funds of the Louisville &amp; Nashville Railroad expended in the State of Alabama for political purposes and charged on the books of the carrier to operating expense?"</p>
    <p>"I will ask you if you know of any funds of the Louisville &amp; Nashville Railroad or the Nashville, Chattanooga &amp; St. Louis Railway expended in the State of Alabama for political purposes and charged on the books of these carriers or on the books of either carrier to construction."</p>
    <p>"I will ask you if you have any knowledge of funds of the Louisville &amp; Nashville Railroad or the Nashville, Chattanooga &amp; St. Louis Railway used for political campaign purposes in the State of Tennessee."</p>
    <p>"Do you know of any funds of the Louisville &amp; Nashville Railroad expended in the State of Tennessee for political campaign purposes and charged on the books of that carrier to operating expense or construction account?"</p>
    <p>The questions are similar to those passed on in the other two cases, and the order is</p>
    <p>Affirmed.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
