<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us275-0518.html" citation="275 U.S. 518" title="COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION v. FIREMAN'S FUND INS. CO.">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p518">518</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION v. FIREMAN'S FUND INS. CO., <a href="./us275-0518.xml#p518">275 U.S. 518</a> (1927)</h1>
    <h2><a href="./us275-0518.xml#p518">275 U.S. 518</a> No. 510. The COMPANY DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. FIREMAN'S FUND INSURANCE COMPANY;</h2>
    <h2>No. 511. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. GLOBE &amp; RUTGERS FIRE INSURANCE COMPANY;</h2>
    <h2>No. 512. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. NORTHWESTERN FIRE &amp; MARINE INSURANCE COMPANY;</h2>
    <h2>No. 513. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. HARTFORD FIRE INSURANCE COMPANY;</h2>
    <h2>No. 514. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. NATIONAL LIBERTY INSURANCE COMPANY;</h2>
    <h2>No. 515. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. AETNA INSURANCE COMPANY;</h2>
    <h2>No. 516. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. WESTERN ASSURANCE COMPANY; [518-Continued.]</h2>
    <h2>No. 517. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. LIVERPOOL &amp; LONDON &amp; GLOBE INSURANCE COMPANY, Ltd.;</h2>
    <h2>No. 518. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. SPRINGFIELD FIRE &amp; MARINE INSURANCE COMPANY;</h2>
    <h2>No. 519. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. FRANKLIN FIRE INSURANCE COMPANY;</h2>
    <h2>No. 520. The COMPANIA DE NAVEGACION, Interior, S. A., petitioner, v. PHOENIX INSURANCE COMPANY.</h2>
    <h2>Supreme Court of the United States</h2>
    <h4>November 21, 1927</h4>
    <p>and</p>
    <p>Mr. John D. Grace, of New Orleans, La., for petitioner.</p>
    <p>Mr. T. Catesby Jones, of New York City, for respondents.</p>
    <p>Petition for writs of certiorari to the United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit granted.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
