<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us230-0512.html" citation="230 U.S. 512" title="Knott v. St. Louis, Kansas City &amp;amp; Colorado R. Co.">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p512">512</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>Knott v. St. Louis, Kansas City &amp; Colorado R. Co., <a href="./us230-0512.xml#p512">230 U.S. 512</a> (1913)</h1>
    <h2>Knott v. St. Louis, Kansas City &amp; Colorado Railroad Company</h2>
    <h2>No. 347, 348</h2>
    <h4>Argued April 1, 2, 3, 1912</h4>
    <h4>Decided June 16, 1913</h4>
    <h2>APPEAL AND CROSS-APPEAL FROM THE CIRCUIT COURT OF THE</h2>
    <h2>UNITED STATES FOR THE WESTERN DISTRICT OF MISSOURI</h2>
    <h2>Syllabus</h2>
    <p>These suits having been consolidated with other similar suits disposed of by the decision in the Missouri Rate Cases, ante, p. <a href="./us230-0474.xml#p474">230 U. S. 474</a>, the same disposition is made of these suits.</p>
    <p>The facts are stated in the opinion.</p>
    <p>Memorandum opinion by direction of the court. By MR. JUSTICE HUGHES.</p>
    <p>This suit was one of the eighteen suits described in the Missouri Rate Cases, ante, p. <a href="./us230-0474.xml#p474">230 U. S. 474</a>. Upon the hearing below, as it appeared that the property of the St. Louis, Kansas City &amp; Colorado Railroad Company had been acquired by the Chicago, Rock Island &amp; Pacific Railway Company, it was ordered by consent of the parties that the suits of the two companies should be consolidated, and that</p>
    <n id="p513">513</n>
    <p>the "findings, statements, and figures as to both companies" should be put "in consolidated form as those of the Chicago, Rock Island &amp; Pacific Railway Company."</p>
    <p>Separate decrees were entered in the two cases, and separate appeals and cross-appeals have been taken.</p>
    <p>The same disposition must be made of both. See Knott v. Chicago, Rock Island, and Pacific Railway Company, sub Missouri Rate Cases, note, p. <a href="./us230-0474.xml#p474">230 U. S. 474</a>, ante. The decree below is therefore reversed, and the cause is remanded, with directions to dismiss the bill without prejudice.</p>
    <p>It is so ordered.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
