<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us459-0086.html" citation="459 U.S. 86" title="GILLETTE CO. v. MINER">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p86">86</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>GILLETTE CO. v. MINER, <a href="./us459-0086.xml#p86">459 U.S. 86</a> (1982)</h1>
    <h4>GILLETTE CO. v. MINER CERTIORARI TO THE SUPREME COURT OF ILLINOIS No. 81-1493. Argued November 10, 1982 Decided December 6, 1982</h4>
    <p>Certiorari dismissed for want of jurisdiction. Reported below: <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/illinois/supreme-court/1981/54211-6.html">87 Ill. 2d 7</a>, <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/illinois/supreme-court/1981/54211-6.html">428 N.E.2d 478</a>.</p>
    <p>Arthur R. Miller argued the cause for petitioner. With him on the briefs were H. Blair White, Russell M. Baird, George A. Platz, and James P. Connolly.</p>
    <p>Robert S. Atkins argued the cause for respondent. With him on the brief were Kenneth P. Ross, Paul Bernstein, and Harry G. Fins.*</p>
    <p>[Footnote *] Briefs of amici curiae urging reversal were filed by Harold D. Shapiro and Duane C. Quaini for the National Association of Independent Insurers et al.; by Joseph D. Alviani and Wayne S. Henderson for the New England Legal Foundation; and by Thomas J. Brandi and C. Delos Putz, Jr., for the plaintiffs in the "Dalkon Shield" IUD Products Liability Litigation et al.</p>
    <p>Briefs of amici curiae urging affirmance were filed by Paul P. Biebel, Jr., First Assistant Attorney General of Illinois, and Kathleen Nogan Morrison and William P. Oberhardt, Assistant Attorneys General, for Tyrone C. Fahner, Attorney General of Illinois, et al.; and by Alan B. Morrison and Frederic Townsend for Public Citizen.</p>
    <p>David B. Kahn, William J. Harte, and Kevin M. Forde filed a brief for the Consumer Coalition as amicus curiae.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>There being no final judgment, the writ of certiorari is dismissed for want of jurisdiction.</p>
    <n id="p87">87</n>
  </opinion>
</case>
