<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us455-0129.html" citation="455 U.S. 129" title="COMMON CAUSE v. SCHMITT">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p129">129</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>COMMON CAUSE v. SCHMITT, (1982)</h4>
    <h2></h2>
    <h4>COMMON CAUSE ET AL. v. SCHMITT ET AL. APPEAL FROM THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA No. 80-847. Argued October 7, 1981 Decided January 19, 1982<a id="nf*1" href="#fn*1">*</a></h4>
    <p><a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp/512/489/2299502/">512 F. Supp. 489</a>, affirmed by an equally divided Court.</p>
    <f n="*1"><a id="fn*1" href="#nf*1">Footnote *</a>
      <p>Together with No. 80-1067, Federal Election Commission v. Americans for Change et al., also on appeal from the same court.</p>
      <p>Archibald Cox argued the cause for appellants in No. 80-847. With him on the briefs were Michael L. Burack, Louis R. Cohen, Roger M. Whitten, Kenneth J. Guido, Jr., and Ellen G. Block.</p>
      <p>Jan W. Baran argued the cause for appellees in both cases and filed a brief for appellees Schmitt et al. Roderick M. Hills, Robert K. Burgess, Robert B. Shanks, and Edward Sonnenschein, Jr., filed a brief for Americans for an Effective Presidency, appellee in No. 80-847. J. Curtis Herge filed a brief for Fund for a Conservative Majority, appellee in No. 80-1067.</p>
      <p>Charles N. Steele argued the cause for the Federal Election Commission, intervenor-appellee in No. 80-847 and appellant in No. 80-1067. With him on the briefs were Kathleen Imig Perkins and Richard B. Bader.Fn</p>
      <p>Fn</p>
      <n id="p129">129</n>
      <p>Briefs of amici curiae urging affirmance were filed by Phillip A. Lacovara, Gerald Goldman, Ronald A. Stern, Charles S. Sims, and Arthur B. Spitzer for the American Civil Liberties Union; and by Wayne T. Elliot and Allen R. Hirons for the Southeastern Legal Foundation, Inc.</p>
      <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
      <p>The judgment is affirmed by an equally divided Court.</p>
      <p>JUSTICE O'CONNOR took no part in the consideration or decision of these cases.</p>
      <n id="p130">130</n>
    </f>
  </opinion>
</case>
