<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us488-0878.html" citation="488 U.S. 878" title="HALE v. OKLAHOMA">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p878">878</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>HALE v. OKLAHOMA, (1988)</h4>
    <h2></h2>
    <h2>Alvie James HALE v. OKLAHOMA. No. 87-7116.</h2>
    <h2>Supreme Court of the United States</h2>
    <h4>October 3, 1988</h4>
    <p>On petition for writ of certiorari to the Court of Criminal Appeals of Oklahoma.</p>
    <p>The petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.</p>
    <p>Justice BRENNAN, dissenting.</p>
    <p>Adhering to my view that the death penalty is in all circumstances cruel and unusual punishment prohibited by the Eighth and Fourteenth Amendments, Gregg v. Georgia, <a href="../us428/us428-0153.xml#p153">428 U.S. 153</a>, 227, 2950, 49 L. Ed. 2d 859 (1976), I would grant certiorari and vacate the death sentence in this case.</p>
    <p>Justice MARSHALL, dissenting.</p>
    <p>Adhering to my view that the death penalty is in all circumstances cruel and unusual punishment prohibited by the Eighth and Fourteenth Amendments, Gregg v. Georgia, <a href="../us428/us428-0153.xml#p153">428 U.S. 153</a>, 231, 2973, 49 L. Ed. 2d 859 (1976) (MARSHALL, J., dissenting), I would grant the petition for writ of certiorari and vacate the death sentence in this case. But even if I believed that the death penalty could be constitutionally imposed under certain circumstances, I would grant the petition and vacate petitioner's death sentence for the same reasons that I expressed in Brecheen v. Oklahoma, <a href="../us485/us485-0909.xml#p909">485 U.S. 909</a> (1988) ( MARSHALL, J., dissenting on denial of certiorari).</p>
    <p>Petitioner was convicted for the murder-kidnaping of the son of a prominent local banking family. Pretrial publicity was extensive. All members of the jury had read or heard of the murder-kidnaping. Some jurors knew petitioner's family and some were acquainted with the victim's family. Six members admitted that they had formed opinions concerning the case. I do not doubt that their representations that they could set aside their opinions and listen to the evidence were sincere. But under the totality of the circumstances, I can only conclude that petitioner Hale, like the petitioner in Brecheen, was denied his constitutional right to a fair trial and to impartial sentencing because of Oklahoma's strong presumption against venue changes.[ Hale v. Oklahoma (1988) ]</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
