<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us439-0008.html" citation="439 U.S. 8" title="Carey v. Wynn">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p8">8</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>Carey v. Wynn, <a href="./us439-0008.xml#p8">439 U.S. 8</a> (1978)</h1>
    <h2>Carey v. Wynn</h2>
    <h2>No. 78-229</h2>
    <h4>Decided October 16, 1978<a href="./us439-0008.xml#p8">439 U.S. 8</a>ast|&gt;*</h4>
    <h2>ON APPEAL FROM THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT</h2>
    <h2>FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF ILLINOIS</h2>
    <h2>Syllabus</h2>
    <p>This Court has no jurisdiction under 28 U.S.C. § 1253 over appeals from a three-judge District Court's declaratory judgment invalidating certain state statutory provisions, such judgment being appealable only to the Court of Appeals.</p>
    <p>Appeals dismissed. Reported below: <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp/449/1302/1640657/">449 F. Supp. 1302</a>.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>A three-judge District Court entered a declaratory judgment holding unconstitutional certain sections of the Illinois Abortion Act of 1975, Ill.Rev.Stat., ch. 38, § 81-21 et seq. (Supp. 1976). Wynn v. Scott, <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp/449/1302/1640657/">449 F. Supp. 1302</a> (ND Ill.1978). The District Court assumed that Illinois prosecutors would recognize and abide by the declaratory judgment, and denied plaintiffs' request for injunctive relief. Id. at 1331.</p>
    <p>The appeals from the declaratory judgment invalidating certain provisions of the statute are dismissed for want of jurisdiction. Title 28 U.S.C. § 1253, the jurisdictional statute under which these appeals are taken, does not authorize an appeal from the grant or denial of declaratory relief alone. Gerstein v. Coe, <a href="../us417/us417-0279.xml#p279">417 U. S. 279</a> (1974). The declaratory judgment is appealable to the Court of Appeals, and we are informed that appeals to that court have been taken.</p>
    <p>Appeals dismissed.</p>
    <p>MR. JUSTICE STEVENS took no part in the consideration or decision of these cases.</p>
    <p>* Together with No. 7239, Diamond v. Wynn et al., also on appeal from the same court.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
