<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<case source="us069-0106.html" citation="69 U.S. 106" title="Humiston v. Stainthorp">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p106">106</n>
    <h>U.S. Supreme Court</h>
    <h>Humiston v. Stainthorp, 69 U.S. 106 (1864)</h>
    <h>Humiston v. Stainthorp</h>
    <h>69 U.S. (2 Wall.) 106</h>
    <h>ERROR TO THE CIRCUIT COURT FOR</h>
    <h>THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF NEW YORK</h>
    <h>Syllabus</h>
    <p>A decree in chancery, awarding to a patentee a permanent injunction, and for an account of gains and profits, and that the cause be referred to a master to take and state the amount, and to report to the court, is not a final decree within the meaning of the act of Congress allowing an appeal on a final decree to this Court.</p>
    <p>Stainthorp and Seguine had filed a bill in the Circuit Court for the Northern District of New York against Humiston for infringing a patent for molding candles, and had obtained a decree against him.</p>
    <p>The decree was that the complainants were entitled to a permanent injunction, and for an account of gains and profits, and that the cause be referred to a master to take and state the amount and report to the court.</p>
    <p>A motion was now made to dismiss the cause for want of jurisdiction.</p>
    <n id="p110">110</n>
    <p>MR. JUSTICE NELSON delivered the opinion of the Court, and after stating the case, said:</p>
    <p>The decree is not final within the act of Congress providing for appeals to this Court according to a long and well settled class of cases, some of which we only need refer to in disposing of the case. <a href="./us069-0106.xml#p106">*</a></p>
    <p>Motion granted.</p>
    <p>* <a href="../us023/us023-0502.xml#p502">The Palmyra</a>, 10 Wheat. 502; <a href="../us048/us048-0650.xml#p650">Barnard v. Gibson</a>, 7 How. 650; <a href="../us054/us054-0011.xml#p11">Crawford v. Points</a>, 13 How. 11; <a href="../us059/us059-0199.xml#p199">Craighead v. Wilson</a>, 18 How. 199; <a href="../us060/us060-0283.xml#p283">Beebe v. Russell</a>, 19 How. 283.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
