<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<case source="us382-0366.html" citation="382 U.S. 366" title="LLOYD v. BRICK">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p366">366</n>
    <h>U.S. Supreme Court</h>
    <h>LLOYD v. BRICK, <a href="./us382-0366.xml#p366">382 U.S. 366</a> (1966)</h>
    <h><a href="./us382-0366.xml#p366">382 U.S. 366</a></h>
    <h>LLOYD v. BRICK ET AL. APPEAL FROM THE COURT OF APPEALS OF MARYLAND. No. 679. Decided January 17, 1966. </h>
    <p>Appeal dismissed and certiorari denied.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The appeal is dismissed for want of jurisdiction. Treating the papers whereon the appeal was taken as a petition for a writ of certiorari, certiorari is denied.</p>
    <n id="p367">367</n>
    <p><a href="./us382-0366.xml#p366">382 U.S. 366</a> (1966) <a href="./us382-0366.xml#p366">382 U.S. 366</a> (1966) "&gt;</p>
    <p>U.S. Supreme Court</p>
    <h>INTERNATIONAL UNION, ELEC., RADIO v. NAT'L LABOR REL., <a href="./us382-0366.xml#p366">382 U.S. 366</a> (1966)</h>
    <p><a href="./us382-0366.xml#p366">382 U.S. 366</a> INTERNATIONAL UNION OF ELECTRICAL, RADIO &amp; MACHINE WORKERS, AFL-CIO v. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD ET AL. ON PETITION FOR WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE SECOND CIRCUIT. No. 87. Decided January 17, 1966.</p>
    <p>Certiorari granted; judgments vacated and remanded.</p>
    <p>Irving Abramson, Benjamin C. Sigal and Winn I. Newman for petitioner.</p>
    <p>Solicitor General Cox, Arnold Ordman, Dominick L. Manoli, Norton J. Come and Laurence S. Gold for National Labor Relations Board, and David L. Benetar and Sanford Browde for General Electric Co., respondents.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The petition for a writ of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit is granted, the judgments are vacated and the case is remanded to that court for further consideration in light of Automobile Workers v. Scofield, ante, p. 205.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
