<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us368-0003.html" citation="368 U.S. 3" title="ABLEMAN v. CITY OF CEDAR RAPIDS">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p3">3</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>ABLEMAN v. CITY OF CEDAR RAPIDS, <a href="./us368-0003.xml#p3">368 U.S. 3</a> (1961)</h1>
    <h4>ABLEMAN ET AL. v. CITY OF CEDAR RAPIDS. APPEAL FROM THE SUPREME COURT OF IOWA. No. 246. Decided October 9, 1961.</h4>
    <p>Appeal dismissed for want of a substantial federal question.</p>
    <p>Reported below: 252 Iowa 948, <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/iowa/supreme-court/1961/50188-0.html">108 N.W.2d 253</a>.</p>
    <p>Ernest F. Pence and Roy A. Golden for appellants.</p>
    <p>C. W. Garberson and William M. Dallas for appellee.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The motion to dismiss is granted and the appeal is dismissed for want of a substantial federal question.</p>
    <n id="p4">4</n>
    <p><a href="./us368-0003.xml#p3">368 U.S. 3</a> (1961) <a href="./us368-0003.xml#p3">368 U.S. 3</a> (1961) "&gt;</p>
    <p>U.S. Supreme Court</p>
    <h4>SECURITY-1ST NAT. BK., LOS ANGELES v. FRANCHISE TAX BD., <a href="./us368-0003.xml#p3">368 U.S. 3</a> (1961)</h4>
    <p><a href="./us368-0003.xml#p3">368 U.S. 3</a> SECURITY-FIRST NATIONAL BANK OF LOS ANGELES ET AL. v. FRANCHISE TAX BOARD OF CALIFORNIA. APPEAL FROM THE SUPREME COURT OF CALIFORNIA. No. 122. Decided October 9, 1961.</p>
    <p>Appeal dismissed and certiorari denied.</p>
    <p>Reported below: <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/california/supreme-court/2d/55/407.html">55 Cal. 2d 407</a>, 359 P.2d 625.</p>
    <p>Pierce Works, Warren M. Christopher, Hugo A. Steinmeyer, Richard E. Sherwood and Brenton L. Metzler for appellants.</p>
    <p>Stanley Mosk, Attorney General of California, James E. Sabine, Assistant Attorney General, and Ernest P. Goodman, Deputy Attorney General, for appellee.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The motion to dismiss is granted and the appeal is dismissed. Treating the papers whereon the appeal was taken as a petition for writ of certiorari, certiorari is denied.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
