<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us368-0349.html" citation="368 U.S. 349" title="NEW YORK CENTRAL RAILROAD CO. v. UNITED STATES">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p349">349</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>NEW YORK CENTRAL RAILROAD CO. v. UNITED STATES, (1962)</h4>
    <h2></h2>
    <h4>NEW YORK CENTRAL RAILROAD CO. v. UNITED STATES ET AL. APPEAL FROM THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE SOUTHERN DISTRICT OF NEW YORK. No. 482. Decided January 8, 1962.</h4>
    <p><a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp/194/947/1943444/">194 F. Supp. 947</a>, affirmed.</p>
    <p>Robert D. Brooks and Alfred A. Green for appellant.</p>
    <p>Solicitor General Cox, Assistant Attorney General Loevinger, Lionel Kestenbaum, Elliott H. Moyer and Robert W. Ginnane for the United States et al., and Clyde B. Aitchison, John R. Turney, Frederick A. Babson, Jr. and John H. Eisenhart, Jr. for the National Freight Traffic Assn., Inc., et al., appellees.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The motions to affirm are granted and the judgment is affirmed.</p>
    <p>(1962) (1962) "&gt;</p>
    <p>U.S. Supreme Court</p>
    <h4>SAVE WAY NORTHERN BOULEVARD, INC. v. NEW YORK, (1962)</h4>
    <p>SAVE WAY NORTHERN BOULEVARD, INC., v. NEW YORK. APPEAL FROM THE COURT OF APPEALS OF NEW YORK. No. 517. Decided January 8, 1962.</p>
    <p>Appeal dismissed for want of a substantial federal question.</p>
    <p>Reported below: <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/new-york/court-of-appeals/1961/10-n-y-2d-727-0.html">10 N.Y.2d 727</a>, 748, 176 N.E.2d 839, 177 N. E. 2d 47.</p>
    <p>Harold H. Levin and Larry M. Lavinsky for appellant.</p>
    <p>Leo A. Larkin and Seymour B. Quel for appellee.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The motion to dismiss is granted and the appeal is dismissed for want of a substantial federal question.</p>
    <n id="p350">350</n>
  </opinion>
</case>
