<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us429-0121.html" citation="429 U.S. 121" title="United States v. Kopp">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p121">121</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>United States v. Kopp, <a href="./us429-0121.xml#p121">429 U.S. 121</a> (1976)</h1>
    <h2>United States v. Kopp</h2>
    <h2>No. 75-1536</h2>
    <h4>Decided December 6, 1976</h4>
    <h2>ON PETITION FOR WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES</h2>
    <h2>COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE TENT CIRCUIT</h2>
    <h2>Syllabus</h2>
    <p>Double jeopardy does not bar the Government's appeal from the District Court's dismissal of an indictment occurring after that court's general finding of guilt in a bench trial.</p>
    <p>Certiorari granted; vacated and remanded.</p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>The operative facts herein are substantially identical to those in United States v. Morrison, ante p <a href="./us429-0001.xml#p1">429 U. S. 1</a>, and United States v. Rose, ante p. <a href="./us429-0005.xml#p5">429 U. S. 5</a>. Respondent's car was stopped by Boarder Patrol agents; a search disclosed marihuana. Respondent lost a motion to suppress and was found guilty after a bench trial. Following this trial, but before sentencing, the District Court, relying upon our decision in Almeida-Sanchez v. United States, <a href="../us413/us413-0266.xml#p266">413 U. S. 266</a> (1973), dismissed the indictment. The Court of Appeals for the Tenth Circuit, as it did in Morrison and Rose, found the Government's appeal barred by double jeopardy.</p>
    <p>In United States v. Wilson, <a href="../us420/us420-0332.xml#p332">420 U. S. 332</a> (1975), we held that double jeopardy would not bar a Government appeal if success on that appeal would result in the reinstatement of a verdict of guilty. The fact that the dismissal of the indictment here occurred after a general finding of guilt rendered by the court in a bench trial, rather than after a return of a verdict of guilty by a jury, is immaterial. Morrison, supra. Double jeopardy therefore does not bar an appeal by the Government.</p>
    <p>We grant the petition for certiorari, vacate the judgment of the Court of Appeals, and remand to that court for proceedings consistent herewith.</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
