<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us438-0906.html" citation="438 U.S. 906" title="CARGAL v. GEORGIA">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p906">906</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>CARGAL v. GEORGIA, <a href="./us438-0906.xml#p906">438 U.S. 906</a> (1978)</h1>
    <h2>Bobby L. CARGAL v. State of GEORGIA No. 77-1426</h2>
    <h2>Supreme Court of the United States</h2>
    <h4>June 26, 1978</h4>
    <p>On petition for writ of certiorari to the Court of Appeals of Georgia.</p>
    <p>The petition for a writ of certiorari is denied.</p>
    <p>Mr. Justice BRENNAN, with whom Mr. Justice STEWART and Mr. Justice MARSHALL join, dissenting.</p>
    <p>Petitioner, convicted of distributing obscene materials under Ga.Code 26-2101 (1975), asks this Court to decide the question:</p>
    <p>"Whether jury instructions on scienter allowing a finding of 'constructive knowledge' in an obscenity case are sufficient to meet . . . constitutional minimum standards . . . ?" Pet. for Cert. 2.</p>
    <p>In Bal ew v. Georgia, <a href="../us435/us435-0223.xml#p223">435 U.S. 223</a> ( 1978), we granted certio-</p>
    <n id="p907">907</n>
    <p>rari to consider, but did not reach, precisely this issue. See Pet. for Cert. in Ballew v. Georgia, O.T.1977, No. 76-761, p. 2. I see no reason to suppose that this issue is any less worthy of consideration on certiorari now than it was when we accepted it in Ballew. For this reason, I would grant certiorari. See also Sewell v. Georgia, <a href="../us435/us435-0982.xml#p982">435 U.S. 982</a>, 98 S. Ct. 1635 (1978) (BRENNAN, J., dissenting from dismissal of appeal); Teal v. Georgia, <a href="../us435/us435-0989.xml#p989">435 U.S. 989</a> ( 1978); Robinson v. Georgia, <a href="../us435/us435-0989.xml#p989">435 U.S. 989</a> ( 1978) (BRENNAN, J., dissenting from vacation of judgment and remand). Barring this, I would grant this petition and summarily reverse. See Ballew, supra, 435 U.S., at 246 (opinion of BRENNAN, J.); Sanders v. Georgia, <a href="../us424/us424-0931.xml#p931">424 U.S. 931</a> (1976) ( dissent from denial of certiorari).</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
