<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us476-0445.html" citation="476 U.S. 445" title="PUBLIC SERVICE COMM'N v. C. &amp; P. TEL. CO.">
  <script src="/assets/js/xslt-polyfill.min.js" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></script>
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p445">445</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h4>PUBLIC SERVICE COMM'N v. C. &amp; P. TEL. CO., (1986)</h4>
    <h2></h2>
    <h4>PUBLIC SERVICE COMMISSION OF MARYLAND v. CHESAPEAKE &amp; POTOMAC TELEPHONE COMPANY OF MARYLAND CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE FOURTH CIRCUIT No. 84-1362. Argued January 13, 1986 Decided May 27, 1986</h4>
    <p><a href="http://cases.justia.com/us-court-of-appeals/F2/748/879/">748 F.2d 879</a>, vacated and remanded.</p>
    <p>Kirk J. Emge argued the cause and filed briefs for petitioner. Jack D. Smith argued the cause for the Federal Communications Commission as amicus curiae urging reversal. With him on the brief were Acting Solicitor General Fried, Deputy Solicitor General Wallace, Christopher J. Wright, Daniel M. Armstrong, and Jane E. Mago.</p>
    <p>D. Michael Stroud argued the cause for respondent. With him on the brief were J. William Sarver, Mark J. Mathis, and Daniel I. Prywes.<a id="nf*1" href="#fn*1">*</a></p>
    <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
    <p>We vacate the judgment of the Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit and remand for further proceedings consistent</p>
    <n id="p446">446</n>
    <p>with the opinion in Louisiana Public Service Comm'n v. FCC, ante, p. 355.</p>
    <p>It is so ordered.</p>
    <p>JUSTICE POWELL and JUSTICE O'CONNOR took no part in the consideration or decision of this case.</p>
    <f n="*1"><a id="fn*1" href="#nf*1">Footnote *</a>
      <p>A brief of amici curiae urging reversal was filed for the State of California et al. by Janice E. Kerr, J. Calvin Simpson, Mark E. Fogelman, Ellen S. LeVine, Joseph I. Lieberman, Attorney General of Connecticut, William B. Gundling, Peter J. Jenkelunas, and Phyllis E. Lemell, Assistant Attorneys General, Howard C. Davenport, Wiliam S. Bilenky, Philip Stoffregen, Patrick Nugent, William Paul Rodgers, Jr., Jack Shreve, Stephen L. Skipper, Robert Waldrum, Joseph G. Donahue, William E. Furber, John K. Keane, Jr., Frank J. Kelley, Attorney General of Michigan, Louis J. Caruso, Solicitor General, Don L. Keskey and Leo H. Friedman, Assistant Attorneys General, Lynda S. Mounts, Brian Moline, Ellyn Elise Crutcher, Michael R. Fontham, and Marshall B. Brinkley.</p>
      <p>A brief of amici curiae urging affirmance was filed for American Telephone and Telegraph Co. et al. by Michael Boudin, Thomas J. Reiman, Vincent L. Sgrosso, W. Preston Granbery, and John B. Messenger.</p>
      <n id="p447">447</n>
    </f>
  </opinion>
</case>
