<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xsl/opinion.xsl"?>
<case source="us408-0913.html" citation="408 U.S. 913" title="LEWIS v. CITY OF NEW ORLEANS">
  <opinion type="Opinions &amp; Dissents">
    <n id="p913">913</n>
    <h2>U.S. Supreme Court</h2>
    <h1>LEWIS v. CITY OF NEW ORLEANS, <a href="./us408-0913.xml#p913">408 U.S. 913</a> (1972)</h1>
    <h2>Mallie LEWIS v. CITY OF NEW ORLEANS. No. 70-5323.</h2>
    <h2>Supreme Court of the United States</h2>
    <h4>June 26, 1972</h4>
    <p>The motion for leave to proceed in forma pauperis is granted.</p>
    <p>The judgment is vacated and the case is remanded to the Supreme Court of Louisiana for reconsideration in light of Gooding v. Wilson, <a href="../us405/us405-0518.xml#p518">405 U.S. 518</a> (1972).</p>
    <p>Mr. Justice POWELL, concurring in the result.</p>
    <p>Under Chaplinsky v. New Hampshire, <a href="../us315/us315-0568.xml#p568">315 U.S. 568</a> (1942), the issue in a case of this kind is whether 'fighting words' were used. Here a police officer, while in the performance of his duty, was called 'G02q d--- M--- F---' police.</p>
    <p>If these words had been addressed by one citizen to another, face to face and in a hostile manner, I would have no doubt that they would be 'fighting words.' But the situation may be different where such words are addressed to a police officer trained to exercise a higher degree of restraint than the average citizen. See Model Penal Code 250.1, Comment 4 (Tent.Draft No. 13, 1961).</p>
    <n id="p914">914</n>
    <p>I see no genuine overbreadth problem in this case for the reasons stated in my dissenting opinion in Rosenfeld v. New Jersey, 405 U.S. 903.</p>
    <p>I would remand for reconsideration only in light of Chaplinsky.</p>
    <p>Mr. Chief Justice BURGER, with whom Mr. Justice BLACKMUN and Mr. Justice REHNQUIST join, dissents; for dissenting opinion see .</p>
    <p>Dissent by Mr. Justice REHNQUIST, with whom THE CHIEF JUSTICE and Mr. Justice BLACKMUN join, dissents; for dissenting opinion see .</p>
  </opinion>
</case>
